Guide to the Ben Sonnenberg Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Ben Sonnenberg Papers,
1956-2001.
Sonnenberg, Ben.
7 linear ft. (14 document boxes)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library New York, NY. 10027
MS#1457
6894663
Ben Sonnenberg, Jr., is a writer and editor best known for founding Grand Street, a New York literary quarterly, which he edited from 1981 until his retirement in 1989; the magazine continued for another fifteen years before it finally ceased publication in the fall of 2004. The bulk of the collection comprises correspondence between Ben Sonnenberg, Jr. and literary contributors associated with Grand Street. Some Grand Street administrative files and a small amount of personal material, including family letters and writings, are also included.
Biographical Note
Native New Yorker Ben Sonnenberg, Jr., is best known as the founder and editor of Grand Street, an influential literary and cultural magazine based in New York City in the mid-1980s and 1990s. Sonnenberg's exposure to the New York literary scene began early in his life: he was the son of Benjamin Sonnenberg, the famous press agent who transformed the family home at 19 Gramercy Place into a central hub for the city's business and literary circles. Sonnenberg both resisted and embraced his cosmopolitan upbringing, recalling his childhood as that of a "younger son in a family of great English furniture." In and out of private schools as a child, he eschewed college in favor of a rigorous program of reading and self-education, traveling abroad and establishing close relations with other writers including W.S. Merwin and Ted Hughes, both with whom he would correspond extensively over the next three decades. In 1963, Sonnenberg completed his first play, Jane Street, shortly before returning to New York to pursue his literary career.
In 1981, Sonnenberg invested his inheritance in founding Grand Street, a "little magazine" dedicated to literature, politics, and cultural criticism. Hailed in the tradition of The Dial and the Partisan Review, Grand Street quickly established itself as a major New York literary organ, with Sonnenberg hosting informal gatherings with friends and contributors at his apartment on Riverside Drive. As an editor, Sonnenberg was known for unprecedented generosity and trust in his writers, as well as his oft-spoken desire to enfranchise rising talent: "[I want] the money to go into their pockets," he frequently said of his contributors. Early contributors included writers like Susan Minot and Anne Carson, whose work he assiduously promoted in Grand Street and through private foundations; the magazine also regularly published works by Edward Said, Arthur Danto, Grover Amen, James Salter, Padgett Powell, James Laughlin, Alice Munro, Edward Sorel, and others.
Through the 1980s, Sonnenberg's work at Grand Street was increasingly inhibited by failing health. He was diagnosed with multiple sclerosis at the age of 34 and spent most of his adult life as a paraplegic, composing his correspondence and literary materials by dictation. Sonnenberg retired from the magazine in 1989; in 1991 he published his memoir, Lost Property: Memoirs and Confessions of a Bad Boy, a well-received account of his adolescence and his subsequent years abroad. Sonnenberg continues to write poetry and film criticism, with essays appearing in Raritan, The Nation, and other venues. He lives in New York with his wife, Dorothy Gallagher.
Scope and Content
The majority of the collection consists of personal and professional correspondence between Ben Sonnenberg, Jr., Grand Street contributors, and other writers associated with the New York literary scene. The correspondence is primarily literary in scope, with writers often responding to criticism of manuscripts and works in progress, as well as providing "updates" on work and home life. In addition to letters from contributors, the series includes letters from other editors-some amicable, others less so-which provide an incisive portrait of the New York literary culture in the mid-1990s.
Also included in the collection are administrative and financial records from Grand Street magazine, manuscripts of Sonnenberg's own work, and a small amount of family and personal correspondence. Overall, the material is in excellent condition, with the exception of newspaper clippings and magazine articles, many of which are acidic and have been either separated or photocopied to preserve their integrity.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in three series.
Series I: Correspondence and Manuscripts, 1956-2001
Series II: Grand Street Administrative Records, 1983-2001
Series III: Personal, 1969-2001
Related Material
The Sally Belfrage Papers
Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Subjects
Amen, Grover.; Carson, Anne.; Danto, Arthur Coleman, 1924-; Hughes, Ted.; Laughlin, James.; Mailer, Norman.; Merwin, W. S.; Minot, Susan.; Munro, Alice.; Powell, Padgett.; Said, Edward.; Salter, James.; Sonnenberg, Benjamin,--Jr.; Sorel, Edward.; New York (State)--Periodicals.; Literature--Periodicals.; Little magazines--Periodicals.; Grand Street.
Access Restrictions
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
Box 8, folders 8 through 10 are restricted until 2022.
Acquisition
Ben Sonnenberg Purchase, May 2002
- Series I: Correspondence and Manuscripts, 1956- 2001
  This series consists of correspondence from the mid-1960s through the 1990s, with a strong emphasis the years immediately following Sonnenberg's retirement as editor of Grand Street magazine (1989-2000). In addition to written correspondence, materials include drafts and manuscripts of written work, photos, drawings, and other ephemera included with written letters. Of particular interest is correspondence with W.S. Merwin, James Salter, James Laughlin, Anne Carson, and Susan Minot, which spans multiple decades and provides a rich glimpse into their respective literary careers. This series is arranged alphabetically.
  - A--General, 1971-2000 (Egbal Ahmad, Colin Amery, Kingsley Amis, Sallie Anderson, Gabriele Annan, Michael Arlen, Toby Armour, William Arrowsmith, Artists Space, James Atlas, Renata Adler) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Adams, Bobby Neal, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Amen, Grover, 1962-1997 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Arbus, Diane, 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - B --General, 1997-2000 (Valerie Borchardt, Elena Brunet, Mark Brown, Eve Bates, Dorothy Braudy, Dierdre Bergson, David Bellos) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Benkert, Ernst, 1998-2001, (3 Folders) (Box 1, Folder 6 to 8)
  - Bernard, Kenneth, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Brennan, Gerald and Gamel, 1960- 1961 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Brophy, Brigid, 1987-1995 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Belfrage, Cedric, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Belfrage, Sally, 1972-1994 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Belfrage, Sally, 1972-1994 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Brown, Saidee, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - C --General, 1968-1999 ("Caldwell," Amy Campitt, Elias Canetti, Colin Campbell, Mary Campbell, Vincent Canby, Aristide Caratzas, E.M. Cioran, Benjamin Cheever, N.A. Choudhury, Angela Conner, Carolyn Cooke, Jane Coola, Alfred Corn, Richard E. Cytowic, Cyril Connolly, Prudence Crowther, Noam Chomsky) (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Carson, Anne, 1987-2001, (5 Folders) (Box 2, Folder 4 to 8)
  - Carson, Anne
    - 1987-2001, (2 Folders) (Box 3, Folder 1 to 2)
    - Autobiography of Red, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Autobiography of Red, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - The Beauty of the Husband, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - General, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Canby, Vincent, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Charkow, Natalie, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Cockburn, Alexander, 1986-1996 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Collins, Billy, 1999-2000 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - D --General, 1969-1994 (Lynn Darling, Hope Hale Davis, Michael DeLisio, Michael Dirda, Tom Dirch, Carl Djerassi, Wilma Dobie, Morris Dickstein, Ethel de Croisset, Mark Doty, Debra Jean Douglas) (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Danto, Arthur, 1989-2000 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Douglas, Keith, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - E --General, 1989-1996 (Richard Eder, Leon Edel, Gavin Ewart, William Eppes) (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Epstein, Helen, 1998-1999 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - F --General, 1989-1996 (Robert Fagles, Harry Ford, Gerry Fremlin, Sue Friedrich, Isabel Fonseca, Anne Frydman, Feldman, Anna Fels) (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Fainlight, Harry and Ruth, 1954- 1997 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Feldman, Irving, 1988-1994 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - General, 1960-1988 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - G--General, 1972-1996 (Fred Gardner, Deborah Garrison, Ron Gault, Alice Rose George, General Electric Young Writers Award, Jack Gilbert, Elise Simon Goodman, Peter Green, Martha Greenwald, Margaret M. Gallette, Red Grooms) (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Gallagher, Dorothy, 2001-2002 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Gardinier, Suzanne, 1989-2000 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Gardinier, Suzanne--The Gathering of Intelligence, 1997 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Gifford, Henry, 1989-1995 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Gill, Brendan, 1970-2000 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Gilliatt, Penelope, 1988-1993 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - H --General, 1960-1997 (Marilyn Hacker, Anna and Philip Hamburger, Josef Hamersky, Michaela Harari, Kent Haruf, Ronald Hayman, John Hess, Lillian Hellman, Greta Hellstrom, Frank Hewitt, Daryl Hime, Christopher Hitchens, Daniel Hoffman, John Hollander, Liz Hollander, Michael Holroyd, Glenn Horowitz, Maureen Howard, Suzanne Hyman, Linell Hanover) (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Haas, Diana, 1995 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Hart, Emma, 1990-2001 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Hauser, Frank, 1962-2001 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Hempel, Amy, 1991-1995 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Hollander, John, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Howard, Richard, 1989-1999 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Hughes, Ted
    - Articles, 1957- 1971 (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Articles and poems, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Books and pamphlets, circa 1966 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - General, 1987-1998 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Photos, 1978-1998 (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Obituaries, 1999 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - I--General, 1971-1987 (Manahnaz Ispahani, Robert Indiana) (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - J--General, 1993-1996 (Thom Jones, Barbara Jones) (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - K--General, 1985-2000 (Walter Kaiser, Murray Kempton, Frances Kiernan, Andrew Kopkind, Karl Kirchwey, Marthe Keller, Hilton Kramer, Andrew Kopkin) (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Kavanagh, Patrick, 1989-1996 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Keeley, Edmund (Mike), 1989-1999 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Kendall, Tim, 1998-2001 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Klawans, Stuart, 1995-2001 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Knox, Bernard, 1989-1999 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - L --General, 1960-1999 (Elinor Langer, Laurie Lee, David Lehman, Robin Lehman, Herb Leibowitz, Wendy Lesser, William Levitan, William Logan, Deacon Derek Lindsay, Bill Logan, Kennett Love, Albert LaFarge, Michael Levey, Michael de Lisio) (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Laughlin, James, 1991-1997 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Leaf, June, 1991-2001 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Lutyens, Elisabeth and Mary, 1961- 1990 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - M--General, 1967-2000 (Norman Mailer, Janet Malcolm, Philip Mansel, Maria Margaronis, Sandy McClatchy, Daniel Mendelsohn, Karl Miller, Rick Moody, Lucas Myers, Elena Margaronis, Charles Monteith, Alex, Carrie Minot Bell, Robert Mitchell) (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - McCullers, Carson, 1957-1958 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Menaker, Daniel, 1990-1999 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Merwin, W.S., 1960-2000 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Michie, James, 1962-1990 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Minot, Susan
    - 1984-2000 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Articles, 1996 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - The Bedroom Ceiling, undated (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Dancing by Myself, 1995 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Dancing by Myself, 1994 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Drawings and Photographs, 1987 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - General, 1986-1999 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Poems, 1995-1996 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Short Stories, 1987-1992 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Morris, Herbert, 2000 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Munro, Alice, 1990-2000 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - N--General, 2001 (Annie Nocenti) (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Nehamas, Alexander, 1997-1998 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Nelson, Graham, 1998 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - O--General, 2000 (Jules Olitski) (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - P --General, 1961-1999 (Francis Partridge, Tom Paulin, John Peet, Martin Peretz, Charles Platt, George Plimpton, Allison Prete, Kathrin Perutz) (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Parker, Robert A., 1997-2001 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Perillo, Lucia, 1998-2001 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Peterson, Lewis, 2000 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Plachy, Sylvia, 1989-2000 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Poirier, Richard, 1987-2000 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Powell, Padgett, 1990-1998 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Quinn, Alice 1995-2000 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - R --General, 1990-1999 (Henry Rago, Raritan (Richard Poirier), Henry Reed, Donald Revell, Adrienne Rich, Robin Robertson, Ned Rorem, Suzanne Ruta, Kitty Ross, Royal Society of Literature) (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Raine, Craig, 1991-2000 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Reid, Christopher, 1991-2000 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Ricks, Christopher, 1969-2000 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Rofihe, Rick, 1989-1997 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - S --General, 1962-2000 (Harvey Sachs, Lee Savage, Nora Sayre, Salvatore Santagati, Senopolous, Mira Schor, Lloyd Schwartz, Elaine Segal, Gilbert Seldes, Roger Shadduck, Israel Shahak, Jim Shepard, Dennis Silk, Alan Silltoe, Michael Silverblatt, Ken Silverstein, Ilena Smith, Yolanda Sonnabend, Pat Strachan, Muriel Spark, Francis Steegmuller, Max Steele, Donald Stewart, Mark Strand, Paul Strand, René Servoise, Marina Somer, Gerald Silk, Jack Shoemaker, Charles Sarka) (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Saba, Fauzi, 1998-2000 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Said, Edward, 1977-2000 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Salter, James, 1973-1998 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Saunders, Frances Stonor, 1997-1998 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Savidis, George, 1975-1999 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Schmidt, Michael, 1997-2001 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Schneider, Stephen, 1999-2001 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Schulman, Grace, 1982-1998 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Sherrill, Robert, 1989-1996 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Sonnenberg, Susanna, 2000 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Sorel, Edward, 1990-2000 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - Steinberg, Saul, 1988-1999 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Stewart, Lucretia, 2000-2001 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Sweeney, Sean, 1997 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - T--General, 1989-2000 (Dorothy Tanning, Eleanor Ross Taylor, William Tester, Deborah Thomas, Lori Toppel, Jeremy Treglown, Holly Eley Treglown, William Trevor, Jeannie Tift) (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Tambimuttu, 1956-1960 (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Tanning, Dorothea, 1998-2000 (Box 10, Folder 16)
  - Thompson, Virgil, 1960-1989 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Train, Michael, 2000 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - U--General, 1997 (George Urban) (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - V--General, 1999-2000 (Minos Volanakis) (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - W--General, 1989-2000 (Scott Wallace, Marina Warner, Robert A. Wilson, Lindsay Waters, Mike Wallace) (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Wolff, Daniel, 1989-1990 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Wade, Sidney, 1983-2001, (4 Folders) (Box 11, Folder 7 to 10)
  - Wade, Sidney--Poems, undated (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - Wheatley, David, 1998-1999 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - Wheelock, John Hall, 1956-1959 (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - Williams, Hugo, 1999-2000 (Box 11, Folder 14)
  - Wypijewski, JoAnn, 1998-1999 (Box 11, Folder 15)
  - XYZ--General, 1991-2000 (T. Yoshida, Gavin Young, Kathleen Zane) (Box 11, Folder 16)
- Series II: Grand Street Administrative Records, 1983- 2001
  Included in this series are administrative and financial records associated with Grand Street, charitable donations and letters from fans and contributors. The materials are arranged alphabetically.
  - A through Z--Contributors, 1983- 1992, (9 Folders) (Box 12, Folder 1 to 9)
  - A through Z--Contributors, 1983-1992 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Donations--Charitable, 1987-1997 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Grand Street
    - Farewells, 1989- 1990 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - General, 1982-1990 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Logo--Drafts, undated (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Grand Street Foundation, 1989-1995 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Guggenheim Foundation, 1989-1990 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Lost Property, 1989-1996 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Prete, Allison, 1995-2001 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Royal Society of Literature, 1994- 1995 (Box 13, Folder 10)
- Series III: Personal, 1969-2001
  Personal materials, including manuscripts of Sonnenberg's writings, and research materials, as well as photos and family correspondence comprise this small series. The materials are arranged alphabetically.
  - Sonnenberg, Ben Jr.
    - "The Crease," 1995-1996 (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - Dog Research, 1991-1994 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Plays--Jane Street, A Childhood Disease, 1963 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Poetry, 1989-1991 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Prose, 1996 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Savage Children's Poems, 1974 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Work--About, 1996 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Financial and Legal, 1977-1994 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Personal--General, 1961-1995 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Tax Returns, 1983-1997, (3 Folders) (Box 8, Folder 8 to 10)
      [Restricted until 2022]
  - Sonnenberg, Ben Sr., 1989-1990 (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Sonnenberg Family, 1969-2001, (2 Folders) (Box 14, Folder 8 to 9)
  - Sonnenberg, Susanna, 1976-1996, (2 Folders) (Box 14, Folder 10 to 11)